<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Leadership on Stein-Otto Svorstøl</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/tags/leadership/</link><description>Recent content in Leadership on Stein-Otto Svorstøl</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 11:41:31 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.svorstol.com/tags/leadership/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Leadership as a platform (team)</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2025/02-03-leadership-as-a-platform/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 11:41:31 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2025/02-03-leadership-as-a-platform/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A couple of years ago I was involved in utilized the ideas from &lt;a href="https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2021/02-14-team-top-at-capra/"&gt;Team Topologies in reorganizing the consultancy where I work&lt;/a&gt;. Recently, Manuel Pais, co-author of &lt;em&gt;Team Topologies&lt;/em&gt;, used my company as an example of something we’ve both called &lt;strong&gt;Leadership as a Platform&lt;/strong&gt;. You can see us mentioned &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=k5SUWdrlTfs&amp;amp;list=PLLwpyIL5FI9wahgmw324EAllojHvOqtb2&amp;amp;t=1376s"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been deeply involved in shifting how we see ourselves—as a &lt;strong&gt;platform&lt;/strong&gt;—and ensuring we maintain that perspective. Instead of treating leadership as a position or a set of management tasks, we emphasize that &lt;strong&gt;anyone&lt;/strong&gt; can take leadership. It’s about stepping up, driving alignment, and enabling others to succeed.&lt;/p&gt;</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A couple of years ago I was involved in utilized the ideas from <a href="https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2021/02-14-team-top-at-capra/">Team Topologies in reorganizing the consultancy where I work</a>. Recently, Manuel Pais, co-author of <em>Team Topologies</em>, used my company as an example of something we’ve both called <strong>Leadership as a Platform</strong>. You can see us mentioned <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=k5SUWdrlTfs&amp;list=PLLwpyIL5FI9wahgmw324EAllojHvOqtb2&amp;t=1376s">here</a>.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been deeply involved in shifting how we see ourselves—as a <strong>platform</strong>—and ensuring we maintain that perspective. Instead of treating leadership as a position or a set of management tasks, we emphasize that <strong>anyone</strong> can take leadership. It’s about stepping up, driving alignment, and enabling others to succeed.</p>
<p>To make this work, we’ve built a dedicated team focused on <strong>alignment and leadership as a platform</strong>—which we call <strong>Team Alignment</strong>. Their mission is to provide services that empower our teams and individuals to take the lead while keeping the organization aligned. They cover many of the tasks of a traditional top management group.</p>
<h2 id="our-approach">Our approach</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Service-Oriented Leadership:</strong> We view leadership activities as <strong>services</strong>, not just tasks. This ensures that all necessary information is accessible and that teams are effectively onboarded into our strategic direction.</li>
<li><strong>Team Responsibility:</strong> Leadership and alignment are collective responsibilities rather than being solely on the shoulders of managers. This fosters a more collaborative and engaged environment.</li>
</ul>
<p>This approach helps us maintain cohesive strategy, ensuring that everyone at Capra remains aligned and informed.</p>
<h3 id="the-services-we-offer">The Services We Offer</h3>
<h4 id="1-company-strategy">1. <strong>Company Strategy</strong></h4>
<p>A living <strong>Notion page</strong> and <strong>slide deck</strong> accessible to everyone. It covers:</p>
<ul>
<li>Who we are: vision, values, and what we do.</li>
<li>Our product and what we sell.</li>
<li>Current market understanding.</li>
<li>Key challenges we foresee.</li>
<li>Guiding policies and priorities for success.</li>
<li>Principles of our organizational model.</li>
<li>This document is continuously updated—always in production, i.e. we just update the documents when we need to.</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="2-metrics-board">2. <strong>Metrics Board</strong></h4>
<p>A <strong>Looker Studio dashboard</strong> offering insights into our goals, performance, and progress.</p>
<h4 id="3-monthly-status--qa-sessions">3. <strong>Monthly Status &amp; Q&amp;A Sessions</strong></h4>
<p>We run monthly status sessions covering company economics, key metrics, and priorities. They are similar to a &ldquo;all hands meeting&rdquo;, with the key difference in how we view them. It&rsquo;s informational, and conversational. It&rsquo;s a service, and we can measure how well it works for our end users.</p>
<h4 id="4-organizational-map">4. <strong>Organizational Map</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Principles and a dynamic perspective of our <strong>team-first organizational model</strong>.</li>
<li>A <strong>Miro board</strong> visualizing our structure and how we operate.</li>
<li>Support in navigating the organization effectively.</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="5-onboarding-for-new-employees">5. <strong>Onboarding for New Employees</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Dedicated onboarding sessions covering all these elements.</li>
<li>Ensures new employees quickly understand our strategy and direction.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="continuous-learning--iteration">Continuous Learning &amp; Iteration</h3>
<p>Through these services, we constantly learn and iterate, improving both our leadership platform and our overall operations.</p>
<p>If this approach resonates with you, or if you’re curious to learn more, feel free to reach out!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>