<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Product on Stein-Otto Svorstøl</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/tags/product/</link><description>Recent content in Product on Stein-Otto Svorstøl</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 15:31:10 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.svorstol.com/tags/product/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Leverage waiting</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2025/04-21-leverage-waiting/</link><pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 15:31:10 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2025/04-21-leverage-waiting/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The last 6 months I have experienced a lot of waiting in one of the teams I&amp;rsquo;m working with. We&amp;rsquo;ve been blocked on deliveries, by either third parties or other teams. Blocked means being unable to move forward as desired. This could things such as some API or software someone else has to develop, or testing on some physical hardware that is not available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being blocked has forced us to reflect and evaluate our approach. Of course we must maintain pressure on those we wait for. This can be done by:&lt;/p&gt;</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The last 6 months I have  experienced a lot of waiting in one of the teams I&rsquo;m working with. We&rsquo;ve been blocked on deliveries, by either third parties or other teams. Blocked means being unable to move forward as desired. This could things such as some API or software someone else has to develop, or testing on some physical hardware that is not available.</p>
<p>Being blocked has forced us to reflect and evaluate our approach. Of course we  must maintain pressure on those we wait for. This can be done by:</p>
<ul>
<li>reach out regularly, and use tickler files to make sure we remember to do so</li>
<li>asking for timelines as a means to be able to time things for yourself</li>
<li>escalating to others internally, who talks with others with the third party</li>
</ul>
<p>It&rsquo;s evident though that this work, even though necessary in many contexts, are not valuable it itself. It&rsquo;s waiting for someone else, and reminding/pushing them.</p>
<p>Our approach is to do those things, but mostly focus on what we can do of valuable work while we wait. What could that be?</p>
<ul>
<li>identify parts that can be built independent of the dependency, i.e. build a happy path first</li>
<li>handle the dependency by mocking or other techniques</li>
<li>prepare for things we know we&rsquo;ll have to do later.</li>
<li>move on to other things, without dependencies, and rework your goals and roadmap</li>
</ul>
<p>It&rsquo;s an awareness thing. We all know we&rsquo;re blocked, but we can leverage the waiting time for something useful and valuable.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Saying no</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2024/08-27-saying-no/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 06:00:29 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2024/08-27-saying-no/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;When working as a leader, and espeically in roles where you handle priorities (such as product management roles), one must be able to say no requests, while at the same time being emptathic to what&amp;rsquo;s being asked. There are many great ideas out there, but we cannot do them all at once. So, let&amp;rsquo;s say you get a big request that your team does not have the bandwith to jump on. How do you respond?&lt;/p&gt;</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>When working as a leader, and espeically in roles where you handle priorities (such as product management roles), one must be able to say no requests, while at the same time being emptathic to what&rsquo;s being asked. There are many great ideas out there, but we cannot do them all at once. So, let&rsquo;s say you get a big request that your team does not have the bandwith to jump on. How do you respond?</p>
<p>What you don&rsquo;t want to do, is straight out say no. That&rsquo;s too hard, and won&rsquo;t come across as empathetic. We rather want to build a story about what we are building or doing , and how that might benefit the organization.  My first steps when asked to deliver on something, I usually do this:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Show our goals</strong>: What are we currently trying to achieve.</li>
<li><strong>Show the roadmap:</strong> Here&rsquo;s our goals, and the activities layed out to fulfill those goals. Show what we&rsquo;re doing, and/or ask what they believe must be removed.</li>
<li><strong>Show what you&rsquo;ve delivered:</strong> I move goals and acitivites to a page where I note down when we delivered on it. I use it to show what we have spent our time on over the last months.</li>
</ol>
<p>This is the beginning of a story around what we are aiming to do, and what we did to go there. Can the requester see their request fit into that story?</p>
<p>Last but not least, I show what can be done to improve the chances of being prioritised. In my experience, stakeholders are willing to invest more in your team or area, but they are unaware of the option. Showing that option, how they can help us get bandwidth to address their issue, is a great approach. But, I would not open with it. If you open with it, the response is usually something along the lines of &ldquo;but what about your current funding?&rdquo;</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>