<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Organizational Design on Stein-Otto Svorstøl</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/tags/organizational-design/</link><description>Recent content in Organizational Design on Stein-Otto Svorstøl</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2023 10:13:16 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.svorstol.com/tags/organizational-design/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Enabling teams vs. platform teams</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2023/enabling-teams-vs.platform-teams/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2023 10:13:16 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2023/enabling-teams-vs.platform-teams/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Updated introduction March 13.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Building a platform is &lt;em>the&lt;/em> way to reduce cognitive load, in various areas. I follow &lt;a href="https://www.thoughtworks.com/what-we-do/enterprise-modernization-platforms-cloud/digital-platform-strategy">the model of ThoughtWorks&lt;/a>, where there are 5 types of platforms. In each, the ideal would be an easy-to-use platform that covers many use cases. That&amp;rsquo;s difficult to do. As with any product (&amp;lsquo;cause think &lt;a href="https://teamtopologies.com/videos-slides/what-is-platform-as-a-product-clues-from-team-topologies">platform as a product&lt;/a>), you&amp;rsquo;ll probably need to &amp;ldquo;sell&amp;rdquo; it, and help users identify if the product fits their needs. You might even help them use it. So, you&amp;rsquo;ll not only be building, but you&amp;rsquo;ll also be a salesman and consultant. At various levels and degrees.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Building an organization for fast flow – delivering often and with high quality</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2022/building-an-organization-for-fast-flow-delivering-often-and-with-high-quality/</link><pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2022 16:51:52 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2022/building-an-organization-for-fast-flow-delivering-often-and-with-high-quality/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Fast flow&lt;/em> is delivering often, with quality and hitting customer needs. How do we know that we are? Accelerate found that the so called DORA-metrics can predict 2x better results in the following areas:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Profitability&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Productivity&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Market share&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Number of customers&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>The &lt;a href="https://www.leanix.net/en/wiki/vsm/dora-metrics#what-are-DORA-metrics">DORA-metrics&lt;/a> are&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Lead time&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Deployment frequency&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Mean time to restore&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Change/fail percentage&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>So, it seems that we should measure and work to improve our ability to deliver often and with quality, because those measures predict better business outcomes.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Solving complex problems as fast as possible</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2021/02-27-solving-complex-problems/</link><pubDate>Sat, 27 Feb 2021 21:43:16 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2021/02-27-solving-complex-problems/</guid><description>&lt;p>As agile methods for software development has been quite widely adopted, the fact that hitting the specification on software is hard, also has been generally accepted. It has been hard, but it is now quite widely accepted that smaller iterations and getting user feedback fast, is crucial to building software that covers actual needs. This means better software, and better products. This trend means that we are starting to recognize that both product and software development are in of itself are complex problems &lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>, where the solution will be emerging over time. It cannot be defined up front. It will also be improved over time, through discovery. This means that it actually not a about the product, nor the software. It is not about business, or earning money. It is about solving complex problems, and doing it faster than anyone else. How?&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Using Team Topologies to reorganize a consultant company</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2021/02-14-team-top-at-capra/</link><pubDate>Sun, 14 Feb 2021 18:03:29 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2021/02-14-team-top-at-capra/</guid><description>&lt;p>In the last year or so I have been involved in reorganizing the company where I work, Capra Consutling, based on the same prinicples as one would want to organize software development. In short, we had an organizations based on roles and hierarchies which made sense when we were no more than 50 employees. When we arrived at 100 employees, it was natural to do some changes, but we did not want to add an extra layer of hierarchy. Therefore, our goal instead was to build a team based organization. We want to create highly autonomous teams, while still maintaining alignment across teams.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>