<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Blogs on Stein-Otto Svorstøl</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/</link><description>Recent content in Blogs on Stein-Otto Svorstøl</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 27 Feb 2021 21:43:16 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.svorstol.com/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Solving complex problems as fast as possible</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2021/02-27-solving-complex-problems/</link><pubDate>Sat, 27 Feb 2021 21:43:16 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2021/02-27-solving-complex-problems/</guid><description>As agile methods for software development has been quite widely adopted, the fact that hitting the specification on software is hard, also has been generally accepted. It has been hard, but it is now quite widely accepted that smaller iterations and getting user feedback fast, is crucial to building software that covers actual needs. This means better software, and better products. This trend means that we are starting to recognize that both product and software development are in of itself are complex problems 1, where the solution will be emerging over time.</description></item><item><title>Using Team Topologies to reorganize a consultant company</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2021/02-14-team-top-at-capra/</link><pubDate>Sun, 14 Feb 2021 18:03:29 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2021/02-14-team-top-at-capra/</guid><description>In the last year or so I have been involved in reorganizing the company where I work, Capra Consutling, based on the same prinicples as one would want to organize software development. In short, we had an organizations based on roles and hierarchies which made sense when we were no more than 50 employees. When we arrived at 100 employees, it was natural to do some changes, but we did not want to add an extra layer of hierarchy.</description></item></channel></rss>