<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Blogs on Stein-Otto Svorstøl</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/</link><description>Recent content in Blogs on Stein-Otto Svorstøl</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 06:00:29 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.svorstol.com/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Saying no</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2024/08-27-saying-no/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 06:00:29 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2024/08-27-saying-no/</guid><description>&lt;p>When working as a leader, and espeically in roles where you handle priorities (such as product management roles), one must be able to say no requests, while at the same time being emptathic to what&amp;rsquo;s being asked. There are many great ideas out there, but we cannot do them all at once. So, let&amp;rsquo;s say you get a big request that your team does not have the bandwith to jump on. How do you respond?&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Syncing articles between Readwise Reader and Pocket</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2024/07-24-readwise-pocket/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2024 17:16:58 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2024/07-24-readwise-pocket/</guid><description>&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m a big reader and I&amp;rsquo;ve used Kindles to read for a long time. I now have a Oasis (best one there is) and Paperwhite (2021). What I don&amp;rsquo;t like is the lock-in, but what I also like is the ecosystem. There&amp;rsquo;s always tradeoffs.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Recently Amazons competitor Kobo released colour e-ink devices, with stylus support. Their styluses, unlike Kindle devices, can write directly in books (not in notes as the Kindle Scribe does). It&amp;rsquo;s more like the Remarkable (without the perfect tactile feel), but in a smaller form factor. Other noteable (fantastic) features are a Pocket-integration and OverDrive support (so one can get books from the library&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>) So I bought a Kobo Libra Colour.&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Mitt produktivitetsystem</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2024/04-08-mitt-produktivitetsystem/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2024 10:58:23 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2024/04-08-mitt-produktivitetsystem/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Jeg har i mange år hatt et system for hvordan jeg styrer hverdagen min, et såkalt produktivitetsystem. Det er ment for å sikre at hodet mitt ikke trenger å huske så mye, og det tilsfredstiller mitt iboende behov og tilbøyelighet for, planmessighet. Her følger en relativt oppdatert versjon av systemet, slik det er akkurat nå. Kanskje det er nyttig for deg?&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="hvorfor-ha-et-produktivitetsystem">Hvorfor ha et &amp;ldquo;produktivitetsystem&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Hodet ditt ikke er ment til å huske på alt mulig hele tiden.&lt;/strong> Du vet alle de ideene og innfallene man kan komme på i tide og utide, ting man gjerne skulle ha gjort eller lignende? Det er påvist å være stressende og distraherende når man skal gjøre en spesifikk ting (se &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Deep-Work-Focused-Success-Distracted/dp/1455586692">Deep Work av Cal Newport&lt;/a>). Som for eksempel når man ser en film, og telefonen lyser opp. Jeg vet ikke med deg, men jeg blir i alle fall nysgjerrig når det skjer. Det er med det samme vanskeligere å følge med på filmen – i alle fall hvis den ikke er &lt;em>helt sinnssykt spennende&lt;/em>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Is there any contradiction between product and agile?</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2023/09-28-is-there-any-contradiction-between-product-and-agile/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Sep 2023 14:59:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2023/09-28-is-there-any-contradiction-between-product-and-agile/</guid><description>&lt;p>A recent &lt;a href="https://www.meetup.com/smidig/events/295796327">event&lt;/a> I was considering visiting, was advertising that there was supposed to be discussion there on product vs. agile., as these were somewhat on a collision course. I do not agree with the premise at all, and I&amp;rsquo;ve thought about the relation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Product is about what to build, i.e. something that hits a need. Agile is about delivering continously, and being able to respond to changes fast. It was a response to waterfall and plan-based development.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Enabling teams vs. platform teams</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2023/enabling-teams-vs.platform-teams/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2023 10:13:16 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2023/enabling-teams-vs.platform-teams/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Updated introduction March 13.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Building a platform is &lt;em>the&lt;/em> way to reduce cognitive load, in various areas. I follow &lt;a href="https://www.thoughtworks.com/what-we-do/enterprise-modernization-platforms-cloud/digital-platform-strategy">the model of ThoughtWorks&lt;/a>, where there are 5 types of platforms. In each, the ideal would be an easy-to-use platform that covers many use cases. That&amp;rsquo;s difficult to do. As with any product (&amp;lsquo;cause think &lt;a href="https://teamtopologies.com/videos-slides/what-is-platform-as-a-product-clues-from-team-topologies">platform as a product&lt;/a>), you&amp;rsquo;ll probably need to &amp;ldquo;sell&amp;rdquo; it, and help users identify if the product fits their needs. You might even help them use it. So, you&amp;rsquo;ll not only be building, but you&amp;rsquo;ll also be a salesman and consultant. At various levels and degrees.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Building an organization for fast flow – delivering often and with high quality</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2022/building-an-organization-for-fast-flow-delivering-often-and-with-high-quality/</link><pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2022 16:51:52 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2022/building-an-organization-for-fast-flow-delivering-often-and-with-high-quality/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Fast flow&lt;/em> is delivering often, with quality and hitting customer needs. How do we know that we are? Accelerate found that the so called DORA-metrics can predict 2x better results in the following areas:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Profitability&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Productivity&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Market share&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Number of customers&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>The &lt;a href="https://www.leanix.net/en/wiki/vsm/dora-metrics#what-are-DORA-metrics">DORA-metrics&lt;/a> are&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Lead time&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Deployment frequency&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Mean time to restore&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Change/fail percentage&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>So, it seems that we should measure and work to improve our ability to deliver often and with quality, because those measures predict better business outcomes.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>OKRs when scaling your organization</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2022/okrs-when-scaling/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2022 13:00:47 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2022/okrs-when-scaling/</guid><description>&lt;p>I recently held a short talk on OKRs, and how their usage develops over time when used in a scaling organization. Here&amp;rsquo;s a summary of the talk, which was in Norwegian. The original slide deck can be found &lt;a href="https://www.svorstol.com/2022/cc22.pdf">here&lt;/a>. Sadly, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t recorded, but here&amp;rsquo;s a summary in English.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So, the starting point here is that I saw a recently released old interview with Steve Jobs in which he talks about how Apple is organized. He says that he has one person responsible for each area and that the teamwork between these people at the top will spread to the rest of the company. The prerequisite for this to work, he says, is trust.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Summary of "Rethinking Agile: Why Agile Teams Have Nothing To Do With Business Agility"</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2022/rethinking-agile/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Jul 2022 12:00:39 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2022/rethinking-agile/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Updated September 27 2023&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I recently read the book &lt;a href="%5Bhttps://www.amazon.com/Rethinking-Agile-Nothing-Business-Agility/dp/3903205397">Rethinking Agile: Why Agile Teams Have Nothing To Do With Business Agility&lt;/a>. I found it useful, and many of the ideas and concepts resonated with me. Usually, I take notes in a Miro-board while I read, but this time I also want to share some notes here, as it might be useful to others. Please note that these are my own notes, so it might be things that I&amp;rsquo;ve missed, or left out. Please reach out if you want to discuss the book and concepts further, or have questions as to why something isn&amp;rsquo;t mentioned. Thanks!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>My setup of filters in Todoist</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2022/my-setup-of-filters-in-todoist/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Jun 2022 10:57:49 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2022/my-setup-of-filters-in-todoist/</guid><description>&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m a big fan of &lt;a href="www.todoist.com">Todoist&lt;/a>, and I&amp;rsquo;ve used it as my main to-do app for around 7 years. I picked it after some extensive research after Wunderlist was bought by Microsoft. Recently a colleague asked me about my setup, Here&amp;rsquo;s a short overview:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>I have one Todoist per project or context, and I sort these into two main projects: Work and Personal.
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>E.g. two engagements become &lt;code>Engagement 1&lt;/code> and &lt;code>2&lt;/code> as subprojects in &lt;code>Work&lt;/code>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If I have several actual projects/initiatives with that engagement, I might have multiple subprojects for that as well.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Each project has two sections: &lt;code>Do Now&lt;/code> and &lt;code>Backlog&lt;/code>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>This enables me to have the following really useful filters:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Overdue first, then inbox, then all work items for today, and finally all personal items for today: &lt;code>overdue, #Inbox, (##Work &amp;amp; today), (##Personal &amp;amp; today)&lt;/code>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Do Now or Backlog for a context: &lt;code>(##Work ) &amp;amp; /Do Now&lt;/code> or &lt;code>(##Work ) &amp;amp; /Backlog&lt;/code>, and similarly with &lt;code>##Personal&lt;/code>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>See &lt;a href="https://todoist.com/help/articles/introduction-to-filters">here&lt;/a> for more on how filters work in Todoist, and more &lt;a href="https://blog.doist.com/todoist-filters">suggestions on use&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Communication and Education in an Agile Transition</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2022/communication-and-education-in-an-agile-transition/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2022 17:49:03 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2022/communication-and-education-in-an-agile-transition/</guid><description>&lt;p>This week I am attending the &lt;a href="https://www.icagile.com/certification/coaching-agile-transitions">ICP-CAT course&lt;/a>. One of the assignments was regarding how to use education and communication in an agile transition. One of the discussions sparked my interest, and I thought more about it after the course. This brought me to a model of how I&amp;rsquo;d address the need for communication and education, that might be useful for others as well.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>From &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Rethinking-Agile-Nothing-Business-Agility/dp/3903205397">Rethinking Agile&lt;/a> we have three levels in an organization [^1]:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Roadmaps in an agile team</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2022/using-a-roadmap-in-an-agile-team/</link><pubDate>Mon, 21 Feb 2022 06:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2022/using-a-roadmap-in-an-agile-team/</guid><description>&lt;p>A colleague and I recently discussed the role of roadmaps in an agile context. He pointed to some books and sources, saying roadmaps are useless or unimportant. This also plays into the #NoEstimates movement.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Specifically, my colleague pointed to the book &amp;ldquo;Inspired&amp;rdquo; by Marty Cagan. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t read the book myself, but I went through the chapters on roadmaps. Here&amp;rsquo;s a relevant quote:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>The issue is that anytime you put a list of ideas on a document entitled “roadmap,” no matter how many disclaimers you put on it, people across the company will interpret the items as a commitment.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>OKRs are not a silver bullet for tracking work</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2022/01-20-okrs-and-metrics/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2022 20:19:02 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2022/01-20-okrs-and-metrics/</guid><description>&lt;p>OKRs are becoming increasingly popular. Most business want to use them for
creating focus, tracking if initiatives to decide if they hit on desired
outcomes, as well as creating alignment in the organisation. Not only for new
initiatives, but across the business. By some, it seems to be looked at as a
silver bullet for tracking work. In my experience, OKRs are not suitable for
everyone and everything. Being clear on when and how you use them, is far more
important than being able to say that one uses them in marketing.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Making decisions often for increased flow everywhere in your organization</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2021/05-26-strategy-and-decisions/</link><pubDate>Wed, 26 May 2021 10:39:47 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2021/05-26-strategy-and-decisions/</guid><description>&lt;p>At the yearly conference of my company (this year held digitally in April), I held a talk on how strategy is about making decisions. In short, I argue that to be able to continuously deliver business value, one must enable all parts of the organization to make small, incremental decisions that align with the whole. I.e. avoid big bang decisions, as well as big bang releases.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In short, I have four suggestions to enable your organization to make smaller decisions, faster and more often:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Solving complex problems as fast as possible</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2021/02-27-solving-complex-problems/</link><pubDate>Sat, 27 Feb 2021 21:43:16 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2021/02-27-solving-complex-problems/</guid><description>&lt;p>As agile methods for software development has been quite widely adopted, the fact that hitting the specification on software is hard, also has been generally accepted. It has been hard, but it is now quite widely accepted that smaller iterations and getting user feedback fast, is crucial to building software that covers actual needs. This means better software, and better products. This trend means that we are starting to recognize that both product and software development are in of itself are complex problems &lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>, where the solution will be emerging over time. It cannot be defined up front. It will also be improved over time, through discovery. This means that it actually not a about the product, nor the software. It is not about business, or earning money. It is about solving complex problems, and doing it faster than anyone else. How?&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Using Team Topologies to reorganize a consultant company</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2021/02-14-team-top-at-capra/</link><pubDate>Sun, 14 Feb 2021 18:03:29 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2021/02-14-team-top-at-capra/</guid><description>&lt;p>In the last year or so I have been involved in reorganizing the company where I work, Capra Consutling, based on the same prinicples as one would want to organize software development. In short, we had an organizations based on roles and hierarchies which made sense when we were no more than 50 employees. When we arrived at 100 employees, it was natural to do some changes, but we did not want to add an extra layer of hierarchy. Therefore, our goal instead was to build a team based organization. We want to create highly autonomous teams, while still maintaining alignment across teams.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>