<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Books on Stein-Otto Svorstøl</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/tags/books/</link><description>Recent content in Books on Stein-Otto Svorstøl</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2023 10:13:16 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.svorstol.com/tags/books/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Enabling teams vs. platform teams</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2023/enabling-teams-vs.platform-teams/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2023 10:13:16 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2023/enabling-teams-vs.platform-teams/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Updated introduction March 13.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Building a platform is &lt;em>the&lt;/em> way to reduce cognitive load, in various areas. I follow &lt;a href="https://www.thoughtworks.com/what-we-do/enterprise-modernization-platforms-cloud/digital-platform-strategy">the model of ThoughtWorks&lt;/a>, where there are 5 types of platforms. In each, the ideal would be an easy-to-use platform that covers many use cases. That&amp;rsquo;s difficult to do. As with any product (&amp;lsquo;cause think &lt;a href="https://teamtopologies.com/videos-slides/what-is-platform-as-a-product-clues-from-team-topologies">platform as a product&lt;/a>), you&amp;rsquo;ll probably need to &amp;ldquo;sell&amp;rdquo; it, and help users identify if the product fits their needs. You might even help them use it. So, you&amp;rsquo;ll not only be building, but you&amp;rsquo;ll also be a salesman and consultant. At various levels and degrees.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Summary of "Rethinking Agile: Why Agile Teams Have Nothing To Do With Business Agility"</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2022/rethinking-agile/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Jul 2022 12:00:39 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2022/rethinking-agile/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Updated September 27 2023&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I recently read the book &lt;a href="%5Bhttps://www.amazon.com/Rethinking-Agile-Nothing-Business-Agility/dp/3903205397">Rethinking Agile: Why Agile Teams Have Nothing To Do With Business Agility&lt;/a>. I found it useful, and many of the ideas and concepts resonated with me. Usually, I take notes in a Miro-board while I read, but this time I also want to share some notes here, as it might be useful to others. Please note that these are my own notes, so it might be things that I&amp;rsquo;ve missed, or left out. Please reach out if you want to discuss the book and concepts further, or have questions as to why something isn&amp;rsquo;t mentioned. Thanks!&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>