<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>management on Stein-Otto Svorstøl</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/tags/management/</link><description>Recent content in management on Stein-Otto Svorstøl</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 21 Feb 2022 06:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.svorstol.com/tags/management/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Roadmaps in an agile team</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2022/using-a-roadmap-in-an-agile-team/</link><pubDate>Mon, 21 Feb 2022 06:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2022/using-a-roadmap-in-an-agile-team/</guid><description>A colleague and I recently discussed the role of roadmaps in an agile context. He pointed to some books and sources, saying roadmaps are useless or unimportant. This also plays into the #NoEstimates movement.
Specifically, my colleague pointed to the book &amp;ldquo;Inspired&amp;rdquo; by Marty Cagan. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t read the book myself, but I went through the chapters on roadmaps. Here&amp;rsquo;s a relevant quote:
The issue is that anytime you put a list of ideas on a document entitled “roadmap,” no matter how many disclaimers you put on it, people across the company will interpret the items as a commitment.</description></item><item><title>OKRs are not a silver bullet for tracking work</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2022/01-20-okrs-and-metrics/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2022 20:19:02 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2022/01-20-okrs-and-metrics/</guid><description>OKRs are becoming increasingly popular. Most business want to use them for creating focus, tracking if initiatives to decide if they hit on desired outcomes, as well as creating alignment in the organisation. Not only for new initiatives, but across the business. By some, it seems to be looked at as a silver bullet for tracking work. In my experience, OKRs are not suitable for everyone and everything. Being clear on when and how you use them, is far more important than being able to say that one uses them in marketing.</description></item><item><title>How I Work</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/work/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2022 00:10:34 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://www.svorstol.com/work/</guid><description>How I work, an informational manual First written January 20, 2022.
Last updated April 28, 2022.
Over the last couple of years, I&amp;rsquo;ve seen people share &amp;ldquo;instruction manuals&amp;rdquo; for themselves shared through their personal websites. I recognize I&amp;rsquo;d value this instructional/informational overview for my own manager, so I might as well provide that for those who I manage, those that I work with, and the managers that I report to. This article summarizes my motivations for doing this nicely, and a few of those that have inspired me are Isaac Hepworth and Den Delimarsky.</description></item></channel></rss>