<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Management on Stein-Otto Svorstøl</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/tags/management/</link><description>Recent content in Management on Stein-Otto Svorstøl</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 06:00:29 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.svorstol.com/tags/management/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Saying no</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2024/08-27-saying-no/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 06:00:29 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2024/08-27-saying-no/</guid><description>&lt;p>When working as a leader, and espeically in roles where you handle priorities (such as product management roles), one must be able to say no requests, while at the same time being emptathic to what&amp;rsquo;s being asked. There are many great ideas out there, but we cannot do them all at once. So, let&amp;rsquo;s say you get a big request that your team does not have the bandwith to jump on. How do you respond?&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Building an organization for fast flow – delivering often and with high quality</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2022/building-an-organization-for-fast-flow-delivering-often-and-with-high-quality/</link><pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2022 16:51:52 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2022/building-an-organization-for-fast-flow-delivering-often-and-with-high-quality/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Fast flow&lt;/em> is delivering often, with quality and hitting customer needs. How do we know that we are? Accelerate found that the so called DORA-metrics can predict 2x better results in the following areas:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Profitability&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Productivity&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Market share&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Number of customers&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>The &lt;a href="https://www.leanix.net/en/wiki/vsm/dora-metrics#what-are-DORA-metrics">DORA-metrics&lt;/a> are&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Lead time&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Deployment frequency&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Mean time to restore&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Change/fail percentage&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>So, it seems that we should measure and work to improve our ability to deliver often and with quality, because those measures predict better business outcomes.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>OKRs when scaling your organization</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2022/okrs-when-scaling/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2022 13:00:47 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2022/okrs-when-scaling/</guid><description>&lt;p>I recently held a short talk on OKRs, and how their usage develops over time when used in a scaling organization. Here&amp;rsquo;s a summary of the talk, which was in Norwegian. The original slide deck can be found &lt;a href="https://www.svorstol.com/2022/cc22.pdf">here&lt;/a>. Sadly, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t recorded, but here&amp;rsquo;s a summary in English.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So, the starting point here is that I saw a recently released old interview with Steve Jobs in which he talks about how Apple is organized. He says that he has one person responsible for each area and that the teamwork between these people at the top will spread to the rest of the company. The prerequisite for this to work, he says, is trust.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Roadmaps in an agile team</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2022/using-a-roadmap-in-an-agile-team/</link><pubDate>Mon, 21 Feb 2022 06:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2022/using-a-roadmap-in-an-agile-team/</guid><description>&lt;p>A colleague and I recently discussed the role of roadmaps in an agile context. He pointed to some books and sources, saying roadmaps are useless or unimportant. This also plays into the #NoEstimates movement.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Specifically, my colleague pointed to the book &amp;ldquo;Inspired&amp;rdquo; by Marty Cagan. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t read the book myself, but I went through the chapters on roadmaps. Here&amp;rsquo;s a relevant quote:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>The issue is that anytime you put a list of ideas on a document entitled “roadmap,” no matter how many disclaimers you put on it, people across the company will interpret the items as a commitment.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>OKRs are not a silver bullet for tracking work</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2022/01-20-okrs-and-metrics/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2022 20:19:02 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2022/01-20-okrs-and-metrics/</guid><description>&lt;p>OKRs are becoming increasingly popular. Most business want to use them for
creating focus, tracking if initiatives to decide if they hit on desired
outcomes, as well as creating alignment in the organisation. Not only for new
initiatives, but across the business. By some, it seems to be looked at as a
silver bullet for tracking work. In my experience, OKRs are not suitable for
everyone and everything. Being clear on when and how you use them, is far more
important than being able to say that one uses them in marketing.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>How I Work</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/work/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2022 00:10:34 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://www.svorstol.com/work/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="how-i-work-an-informational-manual">How I work, an informational manual&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>&lt;em>First written January 20, 2022.&lt;br>
Last updated June 5, 2024.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>Over the last couple of years, I&amp;rsquo;ve seen people share &amp;ldquo;instruction manuals&amp;rdquo; for themselves shared through their personal websites. I recognize that I&amp;rsquo;d value this instructional/informational overview from my manager, so I might as well provide it for those I manage, those I work with, and the managers I report to. &lt;a href="https://www.remotecompany.com/blog/how-to-work-with-me-manual">This article&lt;/a> summarizes my motivations for doing this nicely, and a few of those that have inspired me are &lt;a href="https://github.com/hepwori/wwi/">Isaac Hepworth&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://den.dev/how-i-work/">Den Delimarsky&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>