<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Productivity on Stein-Otto Svorstøl</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/tags/productivity/</link><description>Recent content in Productivity on Stein-Otto Svorstøl</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2024 17:16:58 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.svorstol.com/tags/productivity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Syncing articles between Readwise Reader and Pocket</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2024/07-24-readwise-pocket/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2024 17:16:58 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2024/07-24-readwise-pocket/</guid><description>&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m a big reader and I&amp;rsquo;ve used Kindles to read for a long time. I now have a Oasis (best one there is) and Paperwhite (2021). What I don&amp;rsquo;t like is the lock-in, but what I also like is the ecosystem. There&amp;rsquo;s always tradeoffs.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Recently Amazons competitor Kobo released colour e-ink devices, with stylus support. Their styluses, unlike Kindle devices, can write directly in books (not in notes as the Kindle Scribe does). It&amp;rsquo;s more like the Remarkable (without the perfect tactile feel), but in a smaller form factor. Other noteable (fantastic) features are a Pocket-integration and OverDrive support (so one can get books from the library&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>) So I bought a Kobo Libra Colour.&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Mitt produktivitetsystem</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2024/04-08-mitt-produktivitetsystem/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2024 10:58:23 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2024/04-08-mitt-produktivitetsystem/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Jeg har i mange år hatt et system for hvordan jeg styrer hverdagen min, et såkalt produktivitetsystem. Det er ment for å sikre at hodet mitt ikke trenger å huske så mye, og det tilsfredstiller mitt iboende behov og tilbøyelighet for, planmessighet. Her følger en relativt oppdatert versjon av systemet, slik det er akkurat nå. Kanskje det er nyttig for deg?&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="hvorfor-ha-et-produktivitetsystem">Hvorfor ha et &amp;ldquo;produktivitetsystem&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Hodet ditt ikke er ment til å huske på alt mulig hele tiden.&lt;/strong> Du vet alle de ideene og innfallene man kan komme på i tide og utide, ting man gjerne skulle ha gjort eller lignende? Det er påvist å være stressende og distraherende når man skal gjøre en spesifikk ting (se &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Deep-Work-Focused-Success-Distracted/dp/1455586692">Deep Work av Cal Newport&lt;/a>). Som for eksempel når man ser en film, og telefonen lyser opp. Jeg vet ikke med deg, men jeg blir i alle fall nysgjerrig når det skjer. Det er med det samme vanskeligere å følge med på filmen – i alle fall hvis den ikke er &lt;em>helt sinnssykt spennende&lt;/em>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>My setup of filters in Todoist</title><link>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2022/my-setup-of-filters-in-todoist/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Jun 2022 10:57:49 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.svorstol.com/blog/2022/my-setup-of-filters-in-todoist/</guid><description>&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m a big fan of &lt;a href="www.todoist.com">Todoist&lt;/a>, and I&amp;rsquo;ve used it as my main to-do app for around 7 years. I picked it after some extensive research after Wunderlist was bought by Microsoft. Recently a colleague asked me about my setup, Here&amp;rsquo;s a short overview:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>I have one Todoist per project or context, and I sort these into two main projects: Work and Personal.
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>E.g. two engagements become &lt;code>Engagement 1&lt;/code> and &lt;code>2&lt;/code> as subprojects in &lt;code>Work&lt;/code>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If I have several actual projects/initiatives with that engagement, I might have multiple subprojects for that as well.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Each project has two sections: &lt;code>Do Now&lt;/code> and &lt;code>Backlog&lt;/code>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>This enables me to have the following really useful filters:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Overdue first, then inbox, then all work items for today, and finally all personal items for today: &lt;code>overdue, #Inbox, (##Work &amp;amp; today), (##Personal &amp;amp; today)&lt;/code>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Do Now or Backlog for a context: &lt;code>(##Work ) &amp;amp; /Do Now&lt;/code> or &lt;code>(##Work ) &amp;amp; /Backlog&lt;/code>, and similarly with &lt;code>##Personal&lt;/code>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>See &lt;a href="https://todoist.com/help/articles/introduction-to-filters">here&lt;/a> for more on how filters work in Todoist, and more &lt;a href="https://blog.doist.com/todoist-filters">suggestions on use&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>